All
right, בוקר boker טוב *boker טוב*. So today's דף daf. *daf* is
ל"ח *lamed chet*. We pick up at the bottom of ל"ז עמוד
ב׳ *lamed zayin amud bet*, we're in the middle of a discussion
in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* that somebody who can't get הנאה *hana'ah*
from somebody else, ראובן Reuven *Reuven* can't get הנאה *hana'ah* from שמעון
Shimon, *Shimon*, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* can still teach him תורה Torah, *Torah*
because again, מצוות mitzvot לאו ליהנות ניתנו *mitzvos lav lehenos nitnu* and
תורה Torah *Torah* even though it's a tremendous thing you're giving somebody,
תורה Torah, *Torah* knowledge, but again from a technical perspective that's not
called הנאה *hana'ah*, it's not physical pleasure, it's not monetary pleasure. But
the one thing you can't do is teach him תורה שבכתב Torah
Shebichtav, *Torah she-bichtav*. Why not? Well, either because we're talking about teaching
kids and then that would normally a fee would come with it.
You can't normally charge for teaching תורה שבעל פה Torah Shebe’al Peh,
*Torah she-be'al peh*. But for תורה שבכתב Torah Shebichtav *Torah she-bichtav* you
can charge, either because if you're teaching kids it's the babysitting fee,
or because of the assumption that you're teaching פיסוק טעמים pissuk taamim
*pisuk teamim*, you're teaching the טראפ *trop* which is sort of like
a type of a although necessary for understanding the פסוקים psukim *pesukim*,
not seen as being תורה Torah, *Torah* per se. Sort of the
example we gave about like learning biblical grammar. Okay, and therefore, if
the person is doing that for you and not charging you money,
then he's actually giving you a benefit, he's saving you from the
cost, essentially he's giving you back the fee that he would normally
charge. And I'll just mention the point that Michael mentioned right before
we started, you know the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* says not only although
he cannot teach you this, he can actually he can teach your
sons and daughters. So because that again is which is interesting, right
a I mean he's still saving you money, you don't have to
pay somebody else to teach your sons and daughters, but that's not
something given directly to you, and therefore it's sort of like the
paying off of your creditors which even though it's definitely a benefit
is not something that you're getting directly. What is interesting from that
is that it indicates that a person's daughters were taught תורה Torah.
*Torah*, were taught תורה שבכתב Torah Shebichtav, *Torah she-bichtav*, and and as
Michael is pointing out, according to this read they were also taught
the טראפ *trop*, not necessarily because they were going to do a
ritual reading in the בית כנסת *beis knesses*, but although they in
theory they knew how, that was the famous משנה *Mishnah* that you
know
a ברייתא *braisa* that says that in theory even women should get
עליות *aliyos* except for an issue of what do you call it
of כבוד הציבור *kevod hatzibur* and עליות *aliyos* meant reading from the
תורה Torah. *Torah*, so apparently they had to get the skill somewhere,
but even if that's not why they were being taught it, at
least they were being taught to understand how to grammatically break up
the verse, right, by the how to use with punctuation and therefore
they actually were being taught תורה שבכתב Torah Shebichtav. *Torah she-bichtav* with
the טראפ *trop*, which is as Michael correctly points out just fascinating
to note that phenomenon. So now we pick up with this, whether
this issue of the טראפ *trop* is considered to be תורה Torah,
*Torah* itself. The language the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* uses is דאורייתא *de'oraisa*.
Now you could mean דאורייתא *de'oraisa* literally means דאורייתא *de-oraitha*, the תורה
Torah. *Torah*, whether there's somehow some biblical whether it goes back to
הר סיני Har Sinai. *Har Sinai* is a way of understanding could
be understood, but in the same context it also discusses the תרגום
*Targum* and yes, you could there are ideas approaches that the תרגום
*Targum* goes back to הר סיני Sinai, *Har Sinai*, you know and
all these issues. But in addition to the question of historically when
is it from, it could just mean the question of definition, right,
as we sort of said the other day, would you put biblical
grammar in your לימודי קודש *limudei kodesh* or לימודי חול *limudei chol*,
would you make a ברכת *birchas* would you you had it in
your לימודי קודש *limudei kodesh*, would you make a ברכה *bracha* ברכת
התורה *birchas hatorah* before learning biblical grammar, right, can you learn biblical
grammar in the you know in the bathroom or something. Okay, I
maybe that you can't do because you have to actually be using
biblical words to be learning biblical grammar, but you get the idea.
So the question is is it דאורייתא *de'oraisa*, you know to what
degree is it considered thank you תורה Torah *Torah* itself and therefore
would be subject to this rule about that you know you can't
whether you can or cannot charge money. So according to the approach
that they charged money because of פיסוק טעמים pisuk teamim, *pisuk teamim*
they were allowed to charge, that meant it was not considered תורה
Torah *Torah* per se. Whereas another the other approach would say that
it would be considered תורה Torah, *Torah* per se and you could
not charge for teaching it. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
continues. אמר רבי יצחק *Amar Rabi Yitzchak*,
I'm sorry we just did oh yeah yes, אמר רבי יצחק *amar
Rabi Yitzchak*. So it starts with the word מקרא *Mikra*, it's about
10 lines from the bottom on ל"ז עמוד ב׳ *lamed zayin amud
bet*. So this is based on the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* by נחמיה
*Nechemia*, ויקראו בספר תורת האלקים מפורש ושום שכל ויבינו במקרא *vayikre'u basefer
toras elokim meforash vesum sechel vayavinu bamikra*.
And they understood in the מקרא *Mikra*. So what is the word
מקרא *Mikra*? So before the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said ויבינו במקרא *vayavinu
bamikra*, they understood the מקרא *Mikra* is either the פיסוק טעמים *pisuk
teamim*, is either the טראפ *trop* or it is the מסורת mesoret
*masoret* which presumably means whether the words are written whole or you
know מלא *malei* or חסר *chaseir*. So רבי אמר רבי יצחק *Rabi
amar Rabi Yitzchak* מקרא סופרים soferim, ועיטור סופרים soferim וקריין ולא כתיבן
וכתיבן ולא קריין *Mikra sofrim ve'itur sofrim vekaryan velo
kesivan vekesivan velo karyan*, excuse me he's not going on מקרא *Mikra*
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* but he's saying another point. מקרא סופרים ועיטור
סופרים *Mikra sofrim ve'itur sofrim*, the way the סופרים *sofrim*, the tradition
of the סופרים *sofrim* in terms of how to read the verse,
how to like you know and the adornments of the סופרים *sofrim*
and the things that we'll see, right, וקריין ולא כתיבן וכתיבן ולא
קריין *vekaryan velo kesivan vekesivan velo karyan*, things that are written without
being read... and read without being written, הלכה למשה מסיני halacha lmoshe
misinai. *Halakha l'Moshe miSinai*, all of those, and now we are going
to the question of historically, all of those go all the way
back to משה Moshe מסיני *Moshe miSinai*. Now we're going to unpack
what this statement means. מקרא סופרים *Mikra Sofrim*, so what is מקרא
סופרים *Mikra Sofrim*? ארץ שמים shamayim מצרים *Eretz Shamayim Mitzrayim*. Well, that
was clear. So the Ran says what that means is the way
you read a פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* differently if it's an אתנחתא *Esnachta*,
ארץ *Eretz* or ארץ *Aretz*, right? בורא פרי הגפן *Borei pri hagafen*
or הגפן *hagafen*, okay,
which switches if it's at like the end of a פסוק pasuk
*Pasuk* or at the end of after an אתנחתא *Esnachta*. Now שמים
shamoyim, *Shamayim* and שמים *Shamayim*, I think it also goes from a
פתח *Patach* to a קמץ kamatz *Kamatz*. Am I correct about that?
מצרים מצרים *Mitzrayim Mitzrayim*, anybody here know any grammarians? No, when it
moves from a middle of a פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* to an end
of a פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk*? No, okay, nobody here knows. I'm pretty
sure anyway that's one possibility. The Ran also says what the מצרים
*Mitzrayim* and the שמים *Shamayim* to be is the fact that you
know to read it with a פתח *Patach*, with an ah sound,
even though it's not written that way. Like if people know about
how Yiddish is written, you use, I mean, Yiddish is written sort
of the way English is written, that letters serve as vowels, right?
But in Hebrew, so if you want to write מצרים *Mitzrayim* you
would put like an אלף *Aleph* between the ריש *Reish* and the
מם *Mem*, מצרים *Mitzrayim*, right? But without that אלף *Aleph* you could
read it מצרים *Mitzrim* or something, right? Or or you know in
the same way like מצרים *Metzarim* and שמים שמים *Shamayim Shamayim* you
would put an אלף *Aleph* and so you could write it, I
don't know, שמם *Shamim* or something. So anyway, who knows. So anyway,
to know how to read those words. But where did the Ran
live? In Spain in the 13th century.
So when he says אף על פי שאין בהן אלף נקראין כאילו
היתה בהן *Af al pi she'ein bahen Aleph nikra'in ke'ilu hayta bahen*,
right, that suggests Judeo-Arabic.
Oh, that could be, so the like the Yiddish point I was
making.
Oh excellent, excellent. So he's contrasting it to Judeo-Arabic. I don't know,
the footnotes there say anything because what would have made more sense
would have been the would have been the sort of ארץ ארץ
*Eretz Aretz*, the קמץ kamatz *Kamatz* and the פתח *Patach*.
They
say they said that like שמים מצרים *Shamayim Mitzrayim* or מצרים *Mitzrayim*.
Oh so they say that, right? So I was right about that.
So that works better with the ארץ *Eretz* example. Whether it goes
from a סגול *Segol* to a, you know, ארץ ארץ *Eretz Aretz*
or whether it goes from a פתח *Patach* to a קמץ *Kamatz*.
Okay when it comes at the end of a פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*.
Yes, or first אתנחתא *Esnachta*. אתנחתא *Esnachta*, right. Okay, so that's that.
So let's keep it that reading which is the simpler one. עיטור
סופרים ittur sofrim. *Ittur Sofrim*, what does the crown or adornment of
the scribes mean? אחר achar. תעבורו אחר achar תלך אחר achar תאסף
*Achar ta'avoru, achar teleich, achar te'asef*.
Now what does that mean? So the way the Ran says it
is that you could read the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* in two ways,
right? It says סעדו לבכם אחר תעבורו *Sa'adu libchem achar ta'avoru*. You
know, satiate your hearts and then you shall pass by. But you
could have read it as סעדו לבכם אחר אחר תעבורו *Sa'adu libchem
achar... achar ta'avoru*, after you pass by, right? Is it
satiate your hearts comma then after that you shall pass by? Or
סעדו לבכם אחר תעבורו *Sa'adu libchem achar ta'avoru*, right, if you don't
have a comma after like לבכם *libchem*, then it would be satiate
your hearts after you pass.
But who is it going to be then?
Who knows, right, so that's the point, to know to put the
comma before the אחר תעבורו *achar ta'avoru*, right? So and similarly by
like אחר תלך *achar teleich*, the פסוק Pasuk: *Pasuk* there was... well
right so that's the question, how is this different than the טעם
*Troppe*? Okay תסגר שבעת ימים *Tisager shivat yamim* no what's אחר תלך
*achar teleich*? That's אחר תאסף *achar te'asef*. Where's אחר תלך *achar teleich*?
It sounds like עיטור ittur, סופרים *Ittur Sofrim* means the טעם *Troppe*.
Yeah but that was before but that was presumably what do you
call it, פיסוק טעמים *Pisuk Te'amim*. So here I don't know why
unless here it's very much because it very specifically would have affected
the meaning.
ויאמר אחיה ואמה תשב הנערה אתנו ימים או עשור
אחר תלך *Vayomer achiha v'imah teshev hana'arah itanu yamim o asor achar
teleich*. So again is it and after she should go or let
her sit for us ten days after she goes? Of course none
of that would make sense, okay. Anyway קדמו שרים אחר נוגנים
*Kidmu sarim achar nogunim*. So the the officers preceded after the נוגנים
*nogunim*. So is it קדמו שרים אחר נוגנים *Kidmu sarim achar nogunim*,
first the officers proceeded and afterwards came the נוגנים *nogunim*, how is
it pronounced נוגנים *nogunim*, like musicians, or is it the קדמו שרים
אחר נוגנים *Kidmu sarim achar nogunim*, they passed by in front of
the נוגנים *nogunim*, okay, or they passed by comma and then afterwards
came the נוגנים *nogunim*. צדקתך כהררי אל keharerei el *Tzidkat-cha kehar-rei Eil*.
Now what's צדקתך כהררי אל al. *Tzidkat-cha kehar-rei Eil* going? So is
it the so again the Ran says it's a question of is
it your righteousness is כהררי אל al. *kehar-rei Eil*
like mountains of God? Or is it אל al. צדקתך כהררי *Eil
tzidkat-cha kehar-rei*? Of course the problem is it is הררי אל *har-rei
Eil* because it's סמיכות *smichut* otherwise it would be כהררים *kehar-rerim*. So
oh so the Ran says it's the extra it's the כף *chaf*,
it should have just been צדקתך הררי אל *tzidkat-cha har-rei Eil* because
that would have paralleled the earlier part of the פסוק Pasuk. *Pasuk*.
It's משפטיך תהום רבה *mishpatecha tehom rabah*, right? It's a what is
the difference between a simile and a metaphor? So the first part
was a metaphor, משפטיך תהום רבה *mishpatecha tehom rabah*. So the second
part צדקתך *tzidkat-cha* it should have been הררי אל *har-rei Eil*. So
why is it כהררי אל *kehar-rei Eil*? So
so he says it's תפארת הלשון *tiferet halashon* which is עיטור סופרים
*ittur sofrim* just to somehow I don't know make it sort of
ring. read smoother. It's not exactly clear what the
theme here is that pulls all of these things
together. The other thing the Ran says which would make it all
similar is that the אחרי תבוא is not a question of like
trop and pausing and how to read the verse, but it didn't
need the word אחר. It could have said
סעדו
לבכם ותעבורו, saadu libchem vetaavoru, right? תשב
הנערה
ימים אתנו ותלך. teshev hanara yamim itanu vetelech. מרים תסגר שבעת ימים
ותאסף. Miriam tisager shivat yamim veteaseif. So therefore the אחר just somehow
makes the verse a little more, what's the word, not melodious but
whatever, but it's עיטור, it just sounds better that way and it's
an embellishment that it sounds a little bit better. So anyway all
of that is quite interesting because it means that the difference between
ארץ ארץ שמים מצרים eretz aretz shamayim mitzrayim
is nothing that's written, so you understand why you have to say
this is a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha lmoshe misinai? But here what's
the question? Whether the word אחר belonged in the פסוק pasuk and
you have to insist
that
it belonged in the פסוק pasuk that it wasn't something that was
added later? But that at least combines the idea of like the
כהררי אל also, that all these things are
not were there
originally even though they might seem a little extra. But again the
question what was the הוה אמינא? hava amina? What does it mean
that it was הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha lmoshe misinai? It presumably means
it goes all the way back, the traditions of how to read
these things and so on. But again if it's a question about
whether the words in the actual text, that's strange that you have
to say that.
And these guys כל הני אחר מיותרים הן אלא לתפארת,
kol hani achar meyutarim
hein ella ltiferet, right? We don't need them. It's just it sounds
like he's saying it's a מסורה הלכה למשה מסיני masorah halacha lmoshe
misinai how to read the poetic language of...
Well
no, he has two explanations. One is that some of these words
didn't need to be written. You could have just said ותעבורו, vetaavoru,
ותלך, vetelech, כדמות שערים נוגנים, kedimut searim nognim, or כצדקתך הררי אל.
ketzidkatcha harerei el.
So it's explaining that these were extra embellishments
to make the verse sound better,
but so what? That's nice to know as an interesting point, but
what do you mean by saying it's הלכה למשה מסיני? halakhah le-Moshe
mi-Sinai So presumably it's to exclude from somebody who would say these
came later or something like that. So that's like a funny הוה
אמינא, hava amina, right?
The other explanation is that no, it's a tradition how to read
the פסוק pasuk. where to put the comma so it doesn't make
it confusing. But then the question is how is it different than
the פיסוק טעמים that we were talking about altogether? So anyway two
different explanations here, neither which are fully satisfying. I don't know if
your ArtScroll or English says something to give further some other type
of an approach. Anyway so that's עיטור סופרים. Now, קריין ולא כתיבן,
karyan velo ktivan, things that are read and not written, things that
are read but not written in the
verse. פרת דבלכתו Prat debelachto in the פסוק pasuk. of בלכתו belachto
the Ran quotes here the whole פסוק. pasuk It has the word
פרת Prat which is not written. I'm sorry, which is read but
not written. Let's see if the Ran quotes the פסוק. pasuk בשמואל
להשיב ידו בנהר פרת. Bishmuel lehashiv yado binahar Prat. So it says
to put the hand against the river of פרת. Prat. So פרת
Prat there it doesn't have the word פרת Prat in the verse
but we read it. You know anytime very often you'll see this
in a הפטרה, haftarah, it occurs a lot more in נ"ך Nach
than in the תורה, Torah. you know that there'll be something there
that'll sort of say you know קרי ולא כתיב keri velo ketiv
or כתיב ולא קרי.
ketiv
velo keri.
Right, רות. Ruth. Right, well we're going to get to רות Ruth
in a minute, excellent.
But I mean what happened to the one in
the תורה Torah like אצלו? etzlo? Well that's a good question. So
hold on a minute. פרת דבלכתו. Prat debelachto. איש דכאשר ישאל איש
בדבר האלקים. ish dekaasher yishal ish bidvar haelokim. As a man would
ask after the word of God. So the word איש ish is
not in the verse but it's
read. באים דנבנתה. ba'im denivnetah. So the verse of נבנתה nivnetah in
ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, הנה ימים באים נאם ה' ונבנתה העיר. hineh yamim ba'im
neum Hashem venivnetah hair. So the word באים ba'im is not written
in the verse, it's just הנה ימים נאם ה'. hineh yamim neum
Hashem. Okay but we read
באים. ba'im. לה דפליטה. la depleitah. So the word לה la in
the verse about פליטה pleitah which is the Ran tells us what
is it? בסוף ירמיה בבל יהיה לה לפליטה. besof Yirmiyah Bavel yihyeh
la depleitah. Is Bavel will be for it for a refuge. So
the word לה la is not there but it's read into
it. את דהגד הגד. et dehaged hugad. הגד הגד haged hugad now
moving to רות. Ruth. There you go,
Michael. ויען בעז ויאמר לה הגד הגד לי כל אשר עשית חמותך.
vayaan Boaz vayomer la haged hugad li kol asher asit chamotech. Okay
so the verse just says כל אשר עשית חמותך. kol asher asit
chamotech. But את et obviously is a necessary part there because it
defines what's the object and what's the subject. So the word את
et is read but it's not
written. אלי דהגרן. eilai dehagoren. Okay so we're getting a couple of
רות Ruth here, right? It says ותאמר אליה את כל אשר תאמרי
אלי
אעשה.
vatomer eileha et kol asher tomri
eilai eeseh. What אשר תאמרי אלי אעשה. asher tomri eilai eeseh. And
the next פסוק says... ותרד הגורן. va-tered hagoren. So it just says
אשר תאמרי תעשה asher tomri ta'aseh but it became but we read
תאמרי אלי. tomri alai. Okay, אלי דהשעורים, alai de-has'orim, the verse about
right it says שש השעורים האלה נתן לי כי אמר אלי shesh
has'orim ha-eleh natan li ki amar alai because he said to me
and the word אלי alai is not in the verse but we
read it. Okay. So those are קרין ולא כתבן. keryan ve-lo ktivan.
Those are the ones that are read and not written. וכתבן ולא
קרין, ve-ktivan ve-lo keryan, the ones that are written but not read.
נא דיסלח, na de-yislach, the word where it says יסלח yislach by
where it says what's his name, was it נעמן Na'aman or whatever?
It says בהשתחוותי בית רמון יסלח נא השם לעבדך. be-hishtachawayati beit rimon
yislach na Hashem le-avdecha. So the word נא na is written there
but we don't read we don't read the word נא. na. We
just write יסלח לעבדך yislach le-avdecha instead of please forgive, just
forgive. Top of ל"ח עמוד א'. lamed chet amud alef. זאת דהמצוה.
zot de-hamitzvah. Now this is a question, right? What it's referring to
because if you look at the ר"ן Ran he says בסדר ואתחנן.
be-seder va-etchanan.
It says right, כך
מצאתי כתוב ולא נמצא בספרים שלנו, kach matzati katuv ve-lo nimtza be-sfarim
she-lanu, meaning that this is a claim where the גמרא Gemara says
that something is written and not read and the ר"ן Ran says
actually we don't have this written. Okay. So then there's a question
of trying to identify what exactly the זאת zot is that's being
referred to. I'll read you another ר"ן Ran in a moment.
Okay. גמרא Gemara meaning that the
גמרא Gemara, said it's written but not read and the ר"ן Ran
says we don't have it written. Never written. Well what, כי המצוה,
ki ha-mitzvah, what, המצוה החקים והמשפטים אשר צוה השם. ha-mitzvah ha-chukim ve-ha-mishpatim
asher tziva Hashem.
Yeah,
but then we read the וזאת. ve-zot. We don't have an example
of זאת zot that's with וזאת המצוה ve-zot ha-mitzvah that's written and
not read. Okay. ידרוך דהדורך. yidroch de-hadorech. So in
ירמיה Yirmiyahu it says ידרוך הדורך אש קשתו. yidroch ha-dorech esh kashto.
Okay. So it says ידרוך yidroch twice and the second one is
not read. חמש דפאת נגב chamesh de-pa'at negev by פאת נגב pa'at
negev where it says in במדבר. bamidbar.
אל ידרוך.
al yidroch. What is it? This ידרוך. yidroch. Oh that's better. ידרוך
הדורך את קשתו.
yidroch ha-dorech
et kashto.
Thank you. ידרוך הדורך. yidroch ha-dorech. So what is it? We don't
read it says ידרוך yidroch twice.
He says אל. That's the way that's the way they have it
here.
I think seven.
The word אל. It should be אל הדורך קשתו el ha-dorech kashto
instead of אל ידרוך הדורך. el yidroch ha-dorech. Like the first one
is אל.
Oh it's אל הדורך. el ha-dorech. We take out the word ידרוך.
yidroch. Okay so there's a word ידרוך הדורך yidroch ha-dorech and we
take out the word ידרוך. yidroch. Right it's always the first one
here that we're referring to. Okay.
But the ר"ן Ran says כך מצאתי כתוב. kach matzati katuv. In
other words he found it
but the מנהג minhag was that in
his
שפת דור sefat dor it wasn't written.
Apparently, but I'm not sure which exact פסוק he's referring to. But
we don't have that thing that's written and not read. Okay. Now
חמש דפאת נגב. chamesh de-pa'at negev. So in יחזקאל yechezkel it says
ואלו מדותיה חמש חמש מאות וארבע אלפים. ve-elu midoteha chamesh chamesh me'ot
ve-arba alafim.
So we don't it says חמש chamesh twice we only read חמש
chamesh once. Okay. Now אם דכי גואל
אנכי. im de-ki goel anochi.
So here we go with רות Ruth again. ועתה כי אמנם כי
אם גואל אנכי. ve-atah ki omnam ki im goel anochi.
If I am a גואל goel and we just read the כי
גואל אנכי ki goel anochi for I am a גואל. goel. Alright
so that's the list. הלין כתבן ולא קריין. halin ktivan ve-lo keryan.
Those are the ones that are written and they are not read.
Now first of all I just want to point out to you
something interesting just in this list. Right there's a little repetition in
the list. After the first part of the list it says it
says הני קרין ולא כתבן hani keryan ve-lo ktivan at
the bottom line of ל"ז עמוד ב'. lamed zayin amud bet. הני
קרין ולא כתבן. hani keryan ve-lo ktivan. These are the ones that
are read and not written. וכתבן ולא קרין ve-ktivan ve-lo keryan and
the following are the ones that are written and not read. And
then it repeats it at the end and it says הלין כתבן
ולא קריין. halin ktivan ve-lo keryan. These are the ones that are
written and not read. So the reason is is because you want
to be real like it could easily get confused which list you're
in the middle of. Right and if you just had a whole
list and then you started the next list and said and here
are the ones that are written and not read, somebody could easily
read that here are the ones meaning the ones we just said
above are the ones that are written and not read. So you
want to say as you're transitioning between the two lists, those were
the ones that were like you know read and not written and
these are the ones that were written and not read. Then you
get at the end of your list and you're forgetting which list
you're in the middle of so like it repeats it you know
like it puts an envelope around each list.
Why you're worried about those things that were written?
Exactly. And especially if it's all oral anyway. Now interestingly if you
look at the ר"ן, Ran, okay if you look at the ר"ן,
Ran, the ר"ן Ran says the following. He
says וביסורא u-ve-mesora three lines down in the narrow lines of the
ר"ן, Ran, right which is you know the מסורת lived in what
was it? The בן אשר Ben Asher lived in who lived in
like what was it fifth century, sixth century? Something like that early.
Anyway soon after the ending of the גמרא Gemara, maybe it was
seventh or eighth I lose track. Anyway you know they systematized and
created all these lists of exactly what were the words that had
extra letters, missing letters, what were all the קרי וכתיבs, keri u-chetiv
what were all the כתיב וקריs. chetiv u-keri Right they had a
whole they were they had it all organized. So he says in
that מסורא mesora חשיב כל הני chashiv kol hani it has all
this ותפיא להו אחריני ve-tapya lehu achrinei and it adds other ones.
מיהו לא חשיב mihu lo chashiv את המצוה, et hamitzvah, it doesn't
have the את המצוה et hamitzvah or זאת המצוה. zot hamitzvah. There's
a question about the thing that the גמרא Gemara was referring to
before, אלא זאת, ella zot, the זאת הנפש, zot hanefesh, דכתיב בירמיהו
d'ketiv bi-Yirmiyahu גבי צדקיהו חי השם אשר עשה לנו את הנפש הזאת.
gabei Tzidkiyahu chai Hashem asher asah lanu et hanefesh hazot. So he
takes out the word presumably of הזאת. hazot. So anyway, he says
that the list we have in the מסורה Masorah is actually a
superset of that of the גמרא, Gemara is more than the things
in the גמרא, Gemara which is okay, so the גמרא Gemara is
not necessarily saying everything, might be just using examples, but actually says
there are even some points of divergence that the גמרא Gemara has
some things that aren't
exactly the way it is in the מסורה Masorah that we have.
Now, the other thing I wanted to say about this, because Michael
also points out that there are some other things that are missing
here, like some of the things in the
תורה, Torah עפלים afolim and we read it as טחורים, techorim, but
that's a little bit different, because there, that's called also like a—so
that might not be the same tradition. That tradition of reading words
like ישגלנה ישכבנה, yishgalenah yishkavenah, which are reading words that are softer
because
particularly in the קללות kelalot they're too harsh and they're too explicit,
so that might not be a real tradition that this is how
the word was originally given and intended to be read, that's just
for the ritual קריאה keriah that we are doing in the ציבור,
tzibbur, sort of like there's a הלכה halakhah like you don't read
about מעשה דינה ma'aseh Dinah בציבור, be-tzibbur, right? So there's certain things,
although we do, but okay. But anyway, certain things are just for
the sake of the ציבור tzibbur we're going to read them in
a different way. What? So okay, so that's also sometimes called תיקון
סופרים tikkun soferim as opposed to just like קרי ולא כתיב. qere
v'lo ketiv. So there's all these questions about that, but that's a
category of things that are read differently to be euphemistic, as opposed
to this, this is not about euphemism, so it might be a
different conceptual category. The other interesting thing to point
out—let me ask, let me understand, no one's saying really it's הלכה
למשה מסיני halakhah le-Moshe mi-Sinai. that instead of ישגלנה yishgalenah should be
read ישכבנה? yishkavenah? At some point later there was a
discussion—right.
Right, so that definitely is, and there's actually a very radical רש״י
Rashi on the תורה, Torah if you—I forget where it is, but
you could look for תיקון סופרים tikkun soferim where רש״י Rashi says
something like
תיקון סופרים שתיקנו הסופרים מפני... כדי tikkun soferim she-tikkunu ha-soferim mipnei... k'dei
for the sake of לתיקון הלשון l'tikkun ha-lashon or something like that
where he very much sort of emphasizes that it was like later,
the סופרים, the later scribes sort of—I'll look for the word תיקון
סופרים, tikkun soferim, use your בר אילן, Bar Ilan, I don't remember
where it is in
רש״י Rashi תורה.
Torah No, no.
What period? Well, that's a question also. There is the whether there's
this identifiable class called סופרים and what exact period they live in,
but the point still being it was a later thing, it was
not something—yeah, so that, and look, so that's presumably what the גמרא
Gemara is saying that's not about these. קרי ולא כתיב, qere v'lo
ketiv, the גמרא Gemara is saying there's a tradition, whereas something like—now,
some people will say חס ושלום chas ve-shalom even the thing of
ישכבנה ישגלנה yishkavenah yishgalenah and those things are—totally go all the way
back to סיני, but I'm saying you have somebody as traditional as
רש״י Rashi that seems to indicate otherwise, and that is a different
type of a thing.
What? Well, okay, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't mention everything, but that's
like more of a euphemism type of a thing which it might
be in a different category. The other important thing to note is
about how scholars, biblical scholars, understand this phenomenon of קרי וכתיב. qere
u-ketiv. And the basic way they understand it is—because it's one thing
to say somebody came along and said like, oh, we need to
read this differently, it's too harsh. But how about things like this?
A word נער, na'ar, you have the word נער, na'ar, you don't
have the word נערה. na'arah. How does it develop this idea? So
of course, from a kabbalistic perspective you could say a lot, like
that's very powerful, right? There's like two layers of the text and
they're somehow working together and you could I'm sure say a lot
of interesting things kabbalistically. But the biblical scholars say that there were
actually two different schools of tradition. There were the scribes, there were
the people who their tradition was to preserve like the written text
and it was like handed down father to son or within a
particular
school and you learned how to do the actual art of writing
and making parchment and you learned the whole thing and you had
a tradition of what the written text was. And then there was
a school of people that actually had the tradition
of how to read the text, because the scribes don't necessarily know,
for example, פיסוק טעמים, they don't necessarily know the grammar, right, they
can know the words, they don't necessarily know, right, do you read
it שמים or
שמים, do you put the קמץ here, do you put the קמץ
there? So the skill and the knowledge of how to read is
not necessarily the same as the skill and the knowledge of how
to be a scribe and that art isn't the same. So that
there were actually two different schools. So what happened is, those schools
did not always match up in terms of the written text, right,
the school that had the tradition of reading had the word—didn't have
the word נער, na'ar, and the school that had the tradition of
writing did have the word נער. na'ar. So right, so you've got
those and so that's where these sort of things don't fit together.
So the גמרא Gemara is sort of resolving it by saying, well,
actually it all goes back הלכה halacha למשה מסיני. So both of
these traditions all go all the way back. They're not really in
divergence. Okay. And by the way, I—okay, but that's what the גמרא
Gemara is saying, that they all go back and they were always
these two different ways, a way to write it and a way
to read it. and they didn't always exactly match up. But the
interesting thing I think that's powerful about the way the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* does it is it attributes it to סופרים *Sofrim*, right, מקרא
סופרים *Mikra Sofrim*. So you have the school of the סופרים *Sofrim*
are the scribes, and you're attributing that the way it's read, right,
is with the, you know, is the מקרא *mikra* of the סופרים
*Sofrim*. It's ultimately converging the two. These are not two schools in
opposition, right? The scribal, there's a scribal school but it's a way
of also, you know, it's the way of reading it. So and
ultimately these two things go back, yeah.
We, we assume that סופרים *Sofrim* are scribes, meaning what they mostly
do is write, but it means that they counted words.
Well that's another idea about the סופרים
*Sofrim* I thought, orally and written.
Yeah but I'm not sure the oral, the counting words might have
to do with the מלאים *maleis* and the חסרות *chaseres* which is
very much the scribal activity. So I think actually by saying מקרא
סופרים *Mikra Sofrim* it's the way of bringing those two together, you
know, okay.
So what about these things like the big ו *vav* in
גחון *gachon* and certain things? Yeah, so that's another, okay we'll worry
about that when we get to that, that's another discussion. Right, not
exactly this. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. See, I
bet you never would have thought that this would be a discussion
in נדרים *Nedarim*. So, אמרי רבי יצחק בר אבא *Amrei Rabbi Yitzchak
bar Abba* במערבא *b'Ma'arava* in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* פסקין להדין פסוקא
לתלתא פסוקים psukim, *paskin l'haden pasuka l'telata pesukim*. So here we see
different traditions because we have something which is one פסוק *pasuk*, which
is in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* they read it as three פסוקים
psukim, *pesukim* in terms of where they put the סוף פסוק *sof
pasuk*, they put it in, they make it into three פסוקים pesukim
*pesukim*. What's the פסוק *pasuk*? ויאמר ה' אל משה Moshe הנה אנכי
בא אליך בעב הענן *Vayomer Hashem el Moshe hinne Anochi ba elecha
ba'av he'anan*. That's a pretty big פסוק *pasuk*, right? הנה אנכי בא
אליך בעב הענן בעבור ישמע העם בדברי עמך וגם בך יאמינו לעולם
וישב משה Moshe את דברי העם אל ה' *Hinne Anochi ba elecha
ba'av he'anan ba'avur yishma ha'am b'daberi imach v'gam b'cha ya'aminu l'olam vayyashev
Moshe et divrei ha'am el Hashem*. So certainly those last words וישב
משה Moshe את דברי העם אל ה' *vayyashev Moshe et divrei ha'am
el Hashem* could easily be a separate פסוק *pasuk* and then in
the first part they divided it maybe I don't know where exactly
they would have put the other division. But anyway so that's interesting
acknowledging that there are
different, that there are
different traditions in terms of how to actually do the, you know,
סוף פסוק *sof pasuk* and how to divide the פסוקים psukim, *pesukim*.
We're here, but ויאמר ה' אל משה Moshe?
הנה אנכי בא אליך בעב הענן *Vayomer Hashem el
Moshe hinne Anochi ba elecha ba'av he'anan* period, right.
בעבור ישמע העם בדברי עמך וגם בך יאמינו לעולם *Ba'avur yishma ha'am
b'daberi
imach v'gam b'cha ya'aminu l'olam*.
Yeah but בעבור ישמע העם *ba'avur yishma ha'am* is a funny way
of starting the פסוק *pasuk*. And then the last one is וישב
משה Moshe? וכו' *vayyashev Moshe etc*. Right, that's obvious, that's obvious. Okay
anyway, okay now we get onto some דרשות *drashot* because since we're
talking about scribal activity we're going to talk about some דרשות *drashot*
about משה Moshe. *Moshe* scribing so let's take a look. Okay, אמר
רבי חמא בר חנינא *Amar Rabbi Chama bar Chanina* לא העשיר משה
Moshe? אלא מפסולתן של לוחות luchos *lo he'eshir
Moshe ela mi-psoletan shel luchot*. משה Moshe. *Moshe* got rich from the,
from the dross, from the leftovers, right, of the לוחות *luchot* because
לוחות *luchot* were written according to this on a precious stone like
sapphire and then he scribed it in, he etched in the things,
okay, and he basically, or got etched in it, וכתבתי על הלוחות
*vekatavti al haluchot*, but it, and משה Moshe *Moshe* got to keep
all of the dust, the sapphire dust.
Or it could be larger and you sort of shape it and
carve it.
Oh that's, that's interesting because you're right it works better for the
פסל לך psal lecha, *pesol lecha*. I always thought it was you're
right, it's not but משה Moshe *Moshe* didn't do the writing, משה
Moshe *Moshe* did the פסל *pesal*, he cut out the stones, so
you're right, it would be cutting it out from the larger stone.
Okay, שנאמר shene'emar *she'ne'emar* as it says פסל לך lecha, *pesol lecha*
so carve out for yourself these two stones, שני לוחות אבנים כראשונים
*shnei luchot avanim karishonim* and there is a tradition that those stones
were of a like a precious gem and it's read not just
פסל לך lecha. *pesol lecha* carve out, but פסולתן שלך *psolatan shelcha*
the leftovers is you get to keep for yourself. Okay so יהא
*yehei*, it should be for you. So that's how he got rich.
אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא
*Amar Rabbi Yose bar Chanina* you know
get שכר *s'char* for teaching תורה Torah *Torah*? Excellent, so that is
absolutely on target and that's exactly what the מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha* says.
The מהרש"א *Maharsha* says that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has to say
this because later there'll also be a tradition that משה Moshe *Moshe*
was rich and we just got told that you can't get שכר
*s'char* for teaching תורה Torah *Torah*, so in order that you want
to be curious how did משה Moshe *Moshe* get so rich if
he couldn't get שכר *s'char*, this is how he. Excellent, that's exactly
what the מהרש"א *Maharsha* says. Okay, אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא *Amar
Rabbi Yose bar Chanina* לא ניתנה תורה Torah אלא למשה ולזרעו *lo
nittna Torah ela l'Moshe u'zaro*. In principle, there's a very fascinating גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, the תורה Torah *Torah* was only given for משה Moshe
*Moshe* and his descendants, not for the rest of בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael, *Bnei Yisrael*. שנאמר shene'emar *she'ne'emar* we can figure out what this
means. כתוב לך *ketov lecha*, פסל לך *pesol lecha*. So the same
way פסל לך *pesol lecha* means you get to keep the פסולת
psolet *psolet*, when it says כתוב לך את הדברים האלה *ketov lecha
et hadvarim ha-eleh* it means for you, just for you and for
your descendants, nobody else gets it. So כתוב לך *ketov lecha* מה
פסולתן שלך *ma psoletan shelcha* the same way you get to keep
the leftover of the stones, אף כתבן שלך *af katanvan shelcha* even
the what you've written down is, gets you get to keep. But
wait, let's read a little bit, but משה Moshe נהג בה טובת
עין *Moshe nahag ba tovat ayin*. משה Moshe *Moshe* was very generous.
ונתנה
לישראל *v'nattna l'Yisrael* and he gave it to the larger Jewish people.
ועליו הכתוב אומר omer, *v'alav hakatuv omer* regarding him the תורה Torah
*Torah* says טוב עין הוא יבורך *tov ayin hu yevorach* the generous
eye is the one that shall be blessed. Now, מתיב רב חסדא
*mativ Rav Chisda*, רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* says what? משה Moshe *Moshe*?
It was only given to משה Moshe *Moshe*? What about this פסוק
*pasuk*? ואותי צוה Oti tziva, ה' בעת ההיא ללמד אתכם lelamed etchem,
*v'oti tziva Hashem ba'et ha-hi l'lammed etchem*. God gave it, commanded me
to teach you. So obviously it wasn't given just to משה Moshe
*Moshe*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says... ואותי צוה ה׳, Ve’oti tziva
Hashem,
no, no, no, here's how I would have read the פסוק: God
commanded me ואני לכם, va’ani lachem, and ללמד אתכם, lelamed etchem. that
was my idea. Okay, so ואותי צוה ה׳, God commanded me the
commandments and I chose ללמד אתכם. Obviously very hard to read the
פסוק. Okay, ועתה כתבו לכם את השירה הזאת. Ve’ata kitvu lachem et
hashira hazot. What do you mean? משה Moshe says to them, write
for yourselves,
I'm sorry, ואני למדתי אתכם חקים ומשפטים כאשר צוני ה׳ אלהי, Ve'ani
limadeti etchem chukim umishpatim ka’asher tzivani Hashem Elokai,
I've taught you as God has commanded me. So I've been commanded
to teach you. It wasn't just for me. So the גמרא Gemara
says ואותי צוה, ואני לכם. va’ani lachem. No, the same point, I've
taught you what God has commanded me. God didn't command me to
teach you, God commanded me for me, and I'm being very generous
and I've decided to teach it to you. Okay, ועתה כתבו לכם
את השירה הזאת, Ve’ata kitvu lachem et hashira hazot, write for yourselves
this שירה, shira, which is understood to be the תורה. Torah, So
משה Moshe is giving it over to them, he's telling them to
write it. So the גמרא Gemara says no, השירה לחודה, hashira lachuda,
it just means the שירה shira just האזינו. Ha’azinu. Yeah, okay, האזינו
Ha’azinu you can have, but the rest is for me. Okay, למען
תהיה לי השירה הזאת לעד בבני ישראל. Lema’an tihye li hashira hazot
le’ed bivnei Yisrael. What do you mean? But it says that this
שירה shira will be a testimony and the גמרא Gemara understands that
the testimony incorporates the whole תורה, Torah, although it is funny because
the שירה shira is like a testimony about what happens when they
sin and so on. But anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says clearly
כתבו לכם את השירה הזאת kitvu lachem et hashira hazot refers to
all of the תורה. So and משה Moshe is giving it over
to them, so the גמרא Gemara says it wasn't just his own
choice, apparently he was what he was commanded. So the גמרא Gemara.
now reverses gears and the גמרא Gemara says אלא פלפולא בעלמא. ella
pilpula be’alma. Fine,
fine, fine, so the תורה was always given to be given to
בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, but what משה Moshe had that was given
just to him that he then decided to share was פלפולא בעלמא.
pilpula be’alma. Now פלפול pilpul is like a pepper, right, and it
sort of means like, you know, I don't know, sort of like
you know intricate analysis or something like that, or which is a
very weird shift because what were we talking about initially that was
only given to משה? Moshe Does that mean like the מצוות mitzvot,
weren't intended to be kept by בני ישראל, only to משה? Moshe
So the מהרש״א Maharsha says in keeping with the emphasis of this
thing and in and with the theme of most of the פסוקים
pesukim that the point is the תורה שבכתב, Torah Shebichtav the written
תורה was given to משה. Moshe. Now what does it mean the
תורה שבכתב Torah Shebichtav was given to משה? Moshe. Right, the same
way the פסולת was לך, the כתב ktav is לך. The emphasis
here is on the written words and the תורה שבכתב, Torah Shebichtav.
right? So it could basically mean, and that also if you think
about the end פסוק of כתבו לכם את השירה הזאת, kitvu lachem
et hashira hazot, so it's not a question of who's commanded by
the תורה, right, it's a might be a question of like who
has the תורה שבכתב. Torah Shebichtav So maybe says the מהרש״א, Maharsha,
of course it does throw in here commands, ללמד אתכם חקים ומשפטים.
lelamed etchem chukim umishpatim. So the מהרש״א Maharsha says and this is
quite fascinating because you know before we talked about these two traditions,
the תורה שבכתב Torah Shebichtav, and the reading of it, but there's
also these two traditions as it were or these two schools, right,
תורה שבכתב Torah Shebichtav, and תורה שבעל פה, Torah Shebe’al Peh and
תורה שבעל פה Torah Shebe’al Peh, deriving from תורה שבכתב. Torah Shebichtav,
And if you think about it, most of the time the endeavor
of the גמרא Gemara is basically like משנה and גמרא Gemara is
not, I mean yes the גמרא Gemara eventually says מנא הני מילי
mena hanei mili and gets back into conversation with the פסוקים, but
for the most part the משנה is not in conversation with the
פסוקים, it's just like here's the תורה שבעל פה, Torah Shebe’al Peh,
right? And so the what the מהרש״א Maharsha says is that the
question is the idea of accessing the תורה שבכתב Torah Shebichtav, and
learning from the written word and deriving from the written word what
the הלכה halacha was, that was something that originally was just given
to משה. Moshe We would have had the מצוות, mitzvot, but it
would not somehow have been based on a process of derivation from
the תורה שבכתב, Torah she-bichtav which is like interesting. On the one
hand, you think that like cuts the whole anchor away if all
we have is the הלכה halacha, but without the תורה שבכתב, but
there's this like power that like you know maybe the written word
is so powerful that it has to remain up above in the
divine realm. So משה Moshe got, was right up there with God,
right? משה Moshe went up to the top of הר סיני. So
that protecting of the תורה שבכתב, that would have been for משה
Moshe, and his descendants and that would have sort of kept the
protecting of the divine word separate from the actual practice of the
people. Sort of makes you think of the ancient traditions, right, of
these ancient religions where the priests, right, protected the oracle, protected the
holy thing, the people had the message but they didn't have access.
Or let's talk about the church in the Middle Ages, right? The
church in the Middle Ages, they didn't want to translate the scripture
into the vernacular because it had to be protected by the priest,
it had to be separated by the people. So that's I think
a very powerful read that the מהרש״א Maharsha gives it, where it's
holding up that in theory there could have been this idea that
the written scripture would have been just for משה Moshe and his
descendants, protected, kept separate from the people. And it's not talking about
the הלכה, you know, and the and the מצוות, mitzvot but it's
talking about the written scripture. And then in the end the גמרא
Gemara like gives up on that. And it's a good thing the
גמרא Gemara gives up on that because part of the whole like
you know power, it's not just משה's Moshe generosity, in the end
of course we've given up on that, but it's not just משה's
Moshe generosity, it's in principle this is something that everybody has access
to. And then it turns what משה's Moshe sort of unique gift
was that he shared was in the exact opposite realm. It wasn't
in תורה שבכתב, פלפולא pilpula is like תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba'al
peh some type of... no fancy ability to analyze, that was his
gift and completely shifts by gears and makes what was unique to
him was דווקא davka something that had nothing to do with the
written תורה. So again I think it's very powerful that the הווא
אמינא Havamina the גמרא's Gemara holding out and the power of it
is not just saying that this is maybe that's for like I
said ancient religions or for Christianity in the Middle Ages that's not
for us, but it's also sort of saying but in some degree
maybe in theory there's a reason for an idea like that, meaning
there is this idea of keeping scripture holy and keeping it
and so with all of that power nevertheless it gets democratized, right?
And so that's I think that's a very powerful passage here in
the גמרא. Gemara Yes Michael.
One of those lines, the way I was reading it though not
for that was that really that משה Moshe was the one that
was ראוי Raui since he was he's such a level to keep
all the מצוות mitzvot and he's certainly the Jews backslided a lot,
so much so that it was really going to be מקיים m'kayam
through him given his devotion. But then we say at the end
well look it was meant to be shared with everybody so what
was our whole thing? פלפול בעלמא. Pilpul b'alma. He just said it,
the פלפול. pilpul.
Like oh we were just saying what we just said as פלפול
בעלמא, pilpul b'alma, could be. Anyway, but yes I but I do
think based on the themes and based on the fact that גמרא
Gemara could have quoted a thousand פסוקים to show that we were
all commanded in the מצוות that it's hard to read this גמרא
and based on the larger context to be just like who was
commanded. I think the מהרש"א's read is a very powerful and one
that really fits the theme. Okay so now the גמרא continues. אמר
רבי
יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan אין הקדוש ברוך הוא, ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu,
since talking about משה Moshe being rich, אין הקדוש ברוך הוא משרה
שכינתו אלא על גבור ועשיר וחכם ועניו. ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu mashre
shechinaso ela al gibor v'ashir v'chacham v'anav. God does not cause His
divine presence to rest except on somebody that is mighty physically mighty
and wealthy and wise and with all those things humble. וכולם ממשה,
V'chulam mi-Moshe, all משה Moshe had all of them. גיבור דכתיב Gibor
d'chesiv we know he was powerful and mighty because it says ויפרוש
את
האוהל על המשכן v'yifros es ha-ohel al ha-mishkan he spread out the
tent the covering on top of the משכן. Mishkan. ואמר מר משה
רבינו פירסו V'amar mar Moshe Rabbeinu pirso when it says ויפרוש v'yifros
it means literally he did it. וכתיב עשר אמות אורך הקרש V'chesiv
eser amos orech ha-keresh
how tall was it?
The משכן Mishkan was ten אמות amos high like fifteen feet high.
So if משה Moshe spread it out and didn't say he used
a ladder, so and if he did it all by himself, right,
so he must have been like at least twenty feet high in
order to do it. So you see he must have been very
strong. So the גמרא says right
אימא דאריך וקטין eima
d'arich v'katin
maybe he was tall and thin or tall and weak. Of course
even if it's not just about being tall I mean my God
that thing was so
heavy how long and how heavy was that? So I think that's
a pretty good proof we could have stopped right there. אלא מן
הדין קרא Ela min hadein k'ra from the following פסוק דכתיב ואתפוש
בשני הלוחות d'chesiv va-etpos b'shnei ha-luchos
I grabbed onto the two לוחות ואשליכם מעל שתי ידי va-ashlichem me-al
shtei yadai and I and I cast them from my hands ואשברם
va-ashabrem and I and I broke them. ותניא הלוחות ארכן ששה V'tanya
ha-luchos orchan shisha they were six טפחים tfachim wide
I mean yeah
excuse me long ורחבן ששה v'rochban shisha and six טפחים tfachim wide
so that's like a foot and a half by a foot and
a
half ועוביין שלשה v'ovyan shlosha and three טפחים tfachim thick. So a
foot high a foot and a half high a foot and a
half wide and three טפחים tfachim three טפחים tfachim thick. So what
is that and they were made of stone. So what is that?
1.5 times 1.5 times 3?
No ועוביין שלשה ovyan shlosha just three. No ועוביין שלש עשרה. ovyan
shlosh-ashar. עשיר, ashir, anyway we'll get to עשיר. ashir.
So what is that? It's 1.5 times 1.5 is what is that?
2.25 something times I don't know what is that about
I don't
know
it's something like two and a half cubic feet of stone. Is
that that's pretty heavy I guess. Yeah to hold straight out.
Yeah okay fine. Alright okay anyway okay so the גמרא says like
this okay didn't it say Hashem was supporting those? Yeah that's what
I was wondering too and and that's why
there must be a מדרש midrash not in the פסוק. Okay. Then
עשיר ashir how do we know he was wealthy? פסל לך פסולתן
שלך Psal l'cha psoltan shelcha
carve for you which we said means he got to keep the
leftover stone which was we have a tradition was precious stone.
But wasn't he already with him before that though? What? Meaning this
wasn't the first time he had encounter with God. Didn't they think
he was at some point he got rich not necessarily at the
very beginning.
Oh that's a good point. That came only later. That's a very
good point. I don't know. It's a good point. Okay let's keep
on reading. חכם Chacham how do we know he was wise? Now
this I find quite fascinating. What do you mean how do we
know he was wise? He was משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. Okay but
maybe the point is well who knows maybe משה רבינו's Moshe Rabbeinu
gift was that God spoke to him and God gave him everything
and how do you know that he himself had a high intellect
right? So it's fascinating that the גמרא has to prove that he's
a right?
Like Islam where where Muhammad
right was not
educated but received
and רמב"ם Rambam actually because רמב"ם Rambam in particular understands that נבואה
nevuah is based on on person's intellectual apprehension of God רמב"ם Rambam
has a long discussion at where he rejects people that think oh
no God just has to choose somebody and and give them prophecy
and if God could choose anyone and give them prophecy and רמב"ם
Rambam says no no no it's about your own intellect developing your
intellect to understand God. Right? So here it's sort of saying yeah,
משה had to be wise. How do you know he was wise?
רב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו Rav v'Shmuel d'amri t'ravaihu they both say חמישים
שערי בינה נבראו בעולם. chamishim sha'arei binah nivru ba'olam. There were 50
gates of understanding created in the world. וכולם ניתנו למשה חסר אחת.
vekulam nitnu l'Moshe chasar achat. And משה was given all of them.
Now it's interesting, given, right? Because that actually sounds like it's sort
of Michael's question. You know, was the wisdom before or after? Maybe,
right? So I mean you know God gave משה this wisdom. Okay,
שנאמר as it says I mean God gives everything to everyone, but
anyway, שנאמר ותחסרהו
מעט מאלוקים. vatachasreihu m'at me'elokim. You just made him a little bit
less than God in terms of his intellectual understanding, fell just under
that of God or under fully understanding God. So that's how we
know he was wise. עניו, דכתיב. anav d'chtiv Now notice some of
these are just made are assertions. They're not actually made because they're
really being proven from the פסוקים, right? That's a way of reading
the פסוק. עניו anav, דכתיב d'chtiv. והאיש משה עניו מאד veha'ish Moshe
anav me'od and the man משה was very humble. Okay, that's probably
the easiest one to prove. Okay, but I think Michael does make
a good point, which is like when did he get all of
these qualities and does the it work out timewise in terms of,
you know, in terms of what do you call it, in terms
of when God was משרה mashreh the שכינה. Shechinah. Unless it's just
an assumption like the rich get richer, you know. So if he
was wealthy he obviously must have started off wealthy. Okay, I don't
know, but it's a good point. אמר רבי יוחנן.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan. Yeah.
אמר רבי יוחנן כל הנביאים עשירים היו מנלן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan kol
hanevi'im ashirim hayu minalan. אמר רבי יוחנן כל הנביאים עשירים היו Amar
Rabbi Yochanan kol hanevi'im ashirim hayu all of the prophets were wealthy.
Now it's funny because before we said God is only משרה שכינה
mashreh Shechinah on all of those attributes, so presumably all the נביאים
nevi'im had to have all of those attributes. But now we're just
focusing on the wealth. מנלן minalan where do we
know? ממשה ומשמואל ומעמוס ומיונה. miMoshe u'miShmuel u'miAmos u'miYonah. We can learn
now from these four נביאים nevi'im and then we can make sort
of a general assumption. משה דכתיב Moshe d'chtiv לא חמור אחד מהם
נשאתי. lo chamor echad mehem nasati. I did not sort of take
even one donkey of theirs. So what does it mean I didn't
take? אי בלא אגרא iy blo agra if it means without paying
for the rent לאפוקי
מאן דשקיל בלא אגרא? la'apukei man d'shakal blo agra? So משה has
to say oh I didn't take anything without I didn't steal it,
I didn't take it without rent? Of course he didn't take it
without rent. We don't think משה is a thief. אלא דאפילו באגרא
ela d'afilu b'agra what it means is that I didn't even need
to use one of their donkeys even to pay the I even
to pay the fee, right? I because I had enough donkeys on
my own. So the גמרא says one minute: דילמא משום דעני הוא?
dilma mishum d'anyi hu? If somebody is not renting a car, it
doesn't mean necessarily because he's got his own car. It might mean
because he can't afford to rent a car. So that doesn't prove
anything. So the גמרא says אלא מפסל לך פסולתן יהא שלך. ela
mip'sal lecha psoltan yehei shelcha. So it's from פסל לך, that you
get to keep the leftovers and from there we learn that he
was rich. שמואל דכתיב Shmuel d'chtiv ושמואל אמר הנני ענו בי נגד
ה' ונגד משיחו. veShmuel amar hineni anu bi neged Hashem v'neged meshicho.
Right,
this is what we read in the הפטרה haftarah from this פסוק
we had before, right? את שור מי לקחתי וחמור מי לקחתי. et
shor mi lakachti v'chamor mi lakachti. Who did I take for anybody's
ox or donkey from? אי בחינם iy b'chinam if it means just
taking it without paying for it so לאפוקי מאן דשקיל בחינם? la'apukei
man d'shakal b'chinam? שמואל Shmuel has to say hey I didn't you
know, I'm not a thief, I don't take it for I didn't
take it without paying? Of course not. We wouldn't have had the
הוה אמינא. havah amina. אלא דאפילו בשכר ela d'afilu bischar he means
I didn't take it even by even I didn't even rent it
from them. I didn't even buy it from them. I never tried
to, you know, use my power in any way. So so you
see, how could it be he didn't rent it from them? Must
be he had he had enough for himself. So the גמרא says
no: דילמא דעני הוי? dilma d'anyi havei? Maybe he didn't rent it
because he didn't have any money. אלא מהכא. ela meihacha. Here's from
where we learn now: ותשובתו הרמתה כי שם ביתו. utshuvato haRamatah ki
sham beito. He would return to רמה Ramah because that was his
where his house was. ואמר רבא כל מקום שהלך ביתו עמו. v'amar
Rava kol makom shehalach beito imo. Wherever he would go, his house
would be with him. Now if you normally say that, sounds like
you're poor, right? It's like you're speaking about this guy he's got
his whole all his possessions on his back. Right.
He had an apartment in Marseille and he had an apartment
in Paris.
So yeah, so the way the מפרשים mefarshim read it is is
that if he didn't need to go to anybody's house right, what
does it mean כי שם ביתו? ki sham beito? It means he
never needed anybody's hospitality. How is it that he never needed anybody's
hospitality? Because he came with all of his servants and with all
of his wealth and with all of his provisions and he was
very wealthy. All right, so that's how it's reading it. Okay.
He traveled like a private jet.
Exactly. אמר רבא גדול מה שנאמר בשמואל יותר ממה שנאמר במשה. Amar
Rava gadol mah shene'emar b'Shmuel yoter mimah shene'emar b'Moshe. Before we get
on to the other נביאים nevi'im we're going to contrast these parallel
statements of שמואל Shmuel and משה. Greater is what it says by
שמואל Shmuel יותר ממה שנאמר במשה yoter mimah shene'emar b'Moshe from what
it says by משה. דאילו במשה רבינו כתיב לא חמור אחד מהם
נשאתי. d'ilu b'Moshe Rabbeinu ktiv lo chamor echad mehem nasati. I did
not take even one of their donkeys. דאפילו בשכר d'afilu bischar I
didn't even rent one of their donkeys. Okay. ואילו גבי שמואל אפילו
ברצון לא שכרו. v'ilu gabi Shmuel afilu b'ratzon lo secharo.
Now that נשאתי nasati sort of means like I didn't initiate. I
didn't say to a guy hey do you want to rent me
your donkey? Because who's going to say to משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu
oh no I'm sorry my donkey isn't for rent? Okay. So משה
is saying even though I was willing to pay for it, I
never initiated it because just asking would have been an abuse of
power. That's what משה says. But by שמואל Shmuel it goes even
further, that even if a guy came to me and said to
me: שמואל, Shmuel, would you like to use my donkey? I would
have refused. Even if I wasn't the initiator, I didn't accept.
Even if I would have insisted on paying.
Even if I would have insisted on paying. Okay. אפילו ברצון afilu
b'ratzon so רצון ratzon is not like משה would have forced, but
it means the very asking would have been a certain degree of
abuse of power and creating some sense. of compelling the person. And
שמואל, Shmuel, even if the person himself initiated the rental, שמואל Shmuel
would not have done it. אפילו ברצון לא שכרו. afilu beratzon lo
secharo. To see, so they say, so ויאמרו vayamru and they said
לא עשקתנו ולא רצותנו. lo ashatanu velo ritzotanu. So the word רצותנו
ritzotanu which probably means from more like רצויי ritzuoy of like oppressed
us is being here used as the word of רצון ratzon that
even if we offered you did not want to do it. Okay,
עמוס דכתיב, Amos de-ketiv, עמוס Amos as it says,
ויען עמוס ויאמר אל אמציה לא נביא אנכי ולא בן נביא אנכי
כי בוקר אני vayaan Amos vayomer el Amatzia lo navi anochi velo
ben navi anochi ki boker ani I am a
בוקר boker ובולס שקמים uboles shikmim and a בולס boles of sycamores.
So what is a בוקר boker and a בולס boles of sycamores?
כמאן דתרגם רב יוסף keman de-targem Rav Yosef ארי מרי גיתי אנא,
arei marei getei ana, so בוקר is like from the word בקר
bakar I am a shepherd of cattle. So it's not called a
shepherd. What's it called? An owner. No no no no no but
no no no מרי marei is an owner. Yeah, that's true. Cowboy.
Cowboy anyway cowherd cowherd. But you're right you're right but you're right
no Michael is right. It's not a cowherd. It's מרי, marei, it's
מרי, marei, it's the owner. I am I am an owner of
cattle. Michael's absolutely correct. ושקמים לי בשפלותא veshikmim li beshiflutsa
and I have many trees and sycamore trees in the valley. So
somehow right exactly. יונה דכתיב Yona de-ketiv and יונה Yona says ויתן
שכרה וירד בה vayiten sechara vayered bah
he gave the fee of the boat. ואמר רבי יוחנן שנתן שכרה
של ספינה כולה ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan shenatan sechara shel sefina kulla he
paid for the fee of the whole boat.
Because he thought the storm was going to come? אמר רב רומנוס
שכרה של ספינה הוה ארבע אלפי דינרי דהבא amar Rav Romnus sechara
shel sefina hava arba alfe dinrei de-hava because he wanted to get
moving and they said no no no we gotta sell out all
the tickets. He said forget all the tickets, I'll buy all the
tickets, let's go. Okay, so שכרה של ספינה הוה ארבע אלפי דינרי
דהבא. sechara shel sefina hava arba alfe dinrei de-hava. That's how I
always interpret the מדרש, midrash, I'm not making a joke. Anyway, שכרה
של ספינה הוה ארבע אלפי דינרי דהבא. sechara shel sefina hava arba
alfe dinrei de-hava. The actual rental fee of the whole boat was
four thousand gold dinari. ואמר רבי יוחנן בתחילה היה משה לומד תורה
ומשכחה ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan betchila haya Moshe lomed Torah umeshakecha
originally משה, now here's a very powerful contrast to the idea that
משה was a חכם, chacham, משה originally or maybe this isn't about
the חכם chacham we can talk a minute what it's about, משה
originally would learn the תורה and as soon as he would learn
it he would forget it.
עד שניתנה לו במתנה
ad shenitna lo bematana until it was given to him as a
gift. שנאמר ויתן אל משה ככלתו לדבר אתו shene'emar vayiten el Moshe
ke-chaloto ledaber ito God gave it to משה as a gift. So
it's quite fascinating ending about the idea that he would constantly forget
it. What is that saying? Is it saying that even right does
this idea of a gift does it translate back to the earlier
discussion that you don't teach תורה for a fee? So it's telling
us that all of תורה should be of should be a gift
that even משה's תורה that he received from God, מה אני בחנם
אף אתה בחנם ma ani be-chinam af ata be-chinam the same way
God didn't charge even you know the ability to learn to receive
תורה all of that is maybe every all of our תורה is
a gift from God. So how can we be charging if all
of the תורה that anybody gets is not all through their own
efforts but a gift from God. So to some degree this idea
of gift I think could very much be in conversation with the
earlier point about not charging. I also do wonder if it's also
about this like power of who owns the of like you know
who protects the תורה like it should have been משה and his
children, they should have had it and protected it but it was
given all to us. But then there's this other element which is
like don't make it you know how much is it ours in
terms of our possession fully or is it God's you know that
sense like we really it's so divine that we really wouldn't be
able to hold on to it even משה couldn't hold on to
it unless God was also you know giving it to us as
a gift.
What we just did תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh. or תורה
שבכתב this דף. daf?
Because I if
I made a נדר neder right?
Could you learn this דף? daf?
Could I learn this דף?
Yeah, no, this is I think תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-ba'al peh.
I mean the engagement with the פסוקים is still the תורה שבעל
פה. Yeah.
It's also of interest that the cultural value is that all the
leaders have to be rich.
Yeah, we didn't actually stop to discuss that. What's the point about
rich and wealthy and wise? Right, maybe it's actually you know so
in the sense of leadership right like we know like you know
for better or worse it's sort of like why the משכן Mishkan
and the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash were gold and silver and so
on like that impresses people you know that leaders are tall and
good-looking and all those things and that influences people right? But but
it's funny that and so a נביא navi is not there just
to communicate God's words it's actually to have an impact on the
people so maybe they need some of those qualities. Right, yeah. In
light of Christianity?
Oh, you mean
about the about the עני רכב על חמור ani rocheiv al chamor
type of an idea which is actually a פסוק we have but
yes I got it. But you're right maybe it is in contrast
to that idea of Jesus which is seen as very much in
contrast. But one does wonder is it about leadership or is it
משרה שכינתיה? mashre shechinteih? So maybe the משרה שכינתיה mashre shechinteih also
is it's hard to know what that has to do with being
physically powerful and wealthy and so on, yes.
It's the idea of forgetting until it was given as a gift.
Yeah, maybe there's a sense of the anxiety of experiencing this closeness
with השם Hashem when he's trying to learn. Oh, that's interesting. That's
interesting.
And then he says no don't worry I give it to you.
And then he possesses it and still. Right,
that's very beautiful. Look, I do think that that's a lot of
what this is I mean that's very powerful in terms of the
you know... relationship aspect of it. And I do think a lot
of this is about like, whose תורה is it? Is it God's
תורה, is it our תורה, can we charge for it? Can God—you
know, when משה gets it, can he actually hold it, right? But
God then gives it to him as a gift, so after God
gives it to him as a gift, it is ours, but it's
ours because God has given it to us, right? So I think
that, yeah, that's a very powerful passage here. All right, so now
we go on. Back to הלכות נדרים. Hilchot Nedarim. וזן את אשתו
ואת בניו. Vezan et ishto ve'et banav. So ראובן Reuven can't get
benefit from שמעון, Shimon but שמעון Shimon, can still go ahead and
provide food for ראובן's Reuven wife and kids. Now, even though his
kids might just be seen סתם stam as a טובה tovah because
he might not have a legal obligation to feed his kids, but
he does have a legal obligation to feed his wife. So even
though he's helping him and he's freeing him from his need to
pay the food bill for his wife, which is part of the
כתובה ketubah obligation, nevertheless, it's like paying off a creditor. It's seen
as an indirect benefit, and therefore he is allowed—שמעון Shimon is allowed
to do that for ראובן's Reuven wife and kids. וזן את אשתו
ואת בניו אף על פי שהוא חייב במזונותן, Vezan et ishto ve'et
banav af al pi shehu chayav bimzonotan, even though he has a
legal obligation to feed them. ולא יזון את בהמתו, Velo yazon et
behemto, but he cannot feed his animals, בין טמאה בין טהורה, bein
tmeiah bein tehorah, whether they be kosher or non-kosher animals. Why do
you think the difference is? Why can he not feed the animals?
Personal benefit?
Because if you feed my sheep, you're actually giving me something. Now
I have a fatter sheep. It's worth more. So your—what you gave
directly became increased my wealth. It wasn't just you paid off a
creditor and you gave it to somebody else. You increased some thing
of value of my own. Right? And whether it's a kosher or
non-kosher animal, even if I'm not going to eat it, even a
donkey, you made it a stronger donkey, right? So רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer אומר, omer, זן את הטמאה ואינו זן את הטהורה. zan et
hatmeiah ve'eino zan et hatehorah. No, actually he is allowed to feed
the donkey, because a fatter donkey is not a more valuable donkey.
Okay, now of course the question is, that might be true, but
nevertheless, if the donkey wasn't going to eat, then it would have
been weak and dead. It's worth less too. But again, that might
be seen as indirect. That might be seen as like staving off
a loss rather than actually increasing value. Right now—like right now, my
car, right? If you go ahead and you do a nice paint
job on my car and fix some of the dents, you have
increased the value. But let's say you go ahead and you take
my car to the shop and you get the oil change, which
it needs, right? So did you increase the value? No. If you
wouldn't have done the oil change, it would have, you know, it
might have ruined the engine eventually and it could have hurt the
value, but what you did right now didn't actually—maintenance, right? You actually
did not increase the value. So that could be what he is
saying. The ר"ן Ran chooses to read it not that way. The
ר"ן Ran says he's talking about only if the donkey already has
its basic diet and what you're doing is you're giving it extra
food. So extra food the donkey doesn't need, but the ר"ן Ran
says you would not be allowed to—and it's not increasing its value
to me. But giving it its basic diet, he says, would be
giving me something of value. But again, I'm not sure that's necessarily
פשט. pshat. The פשט pshat might be that that's just preventing a
loss, that's not actually right now increasing value. Okay.
The רישא reisha is—the רישא reisha is you're the מודר הנאה mudar
hana'ah
but you can still feed my wife. Yes.
ראובן Reuven can't get benefit from שמעון, but שמעון can still feed
ראובן's Reuven wife. Right.
Because ראובן Reuven has the חיוב chiyuv to provide for his wife.
Right. That's like paying off a creditor, but it doesn't actually increase
ראובן's Reuven value, you know, net worth, give something ראובן Reuven directly
of value, okay? But feeding the animals does increase the value of
ראובן's property. Okay? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר, זן את הטמאה ואינו
זן את הטהורה. zan et hatmeiah ve'eino zan et hatehorah. אמרו לו,
Amru lo, they said to him, מה בין טמאה לטהורה? ma bein
tmeiah letehorah? What's the difference? אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said back
to them, שהטהורה נפשה לשמים וגופה שלו. shehatehorah nafsha lashamayim vegufa shelo.
That's a very interesting way of saying it. Because a kosher animal,
its soul goes up to heaven. And here you see, if anybody
like any animal lovers want to know, do animals get עולם הבא?
Olam HaBa? Its soul goes up to heaven, okay? But the body
you get to eat. So therefore when the body is fatter or
whatever, that's an increase of your value. וטמאה, Utmeiah, but the non-kosher
animal, נפשה וגופה לשמים, nafsha vegufa lashamayim,
it all goes up to heaven. You don't get to eat it.
So having a fatter donkey doesn't do you any good. Okay. אמרו
לו, Amru lo, they said back to him, אף הטמאה נפשה לשמים
וגופה שלו. af hatmeiah nafsha lashamayim vegufa shelo. No,
here even also actually just a fatter donkey does you some good,
שאם ירצה הרי הוא מוכרה לעובדי כוכבים ומאכילה לכלבים, she'im yirtzeh harei
hu mochrah le'ovdei chochavim uma'achilah leklavim,
because with a dead donkey you can still sell it to non-Jews
or use it as dog food. So even just an increase in
the, you know, in the—in the size of the animal, right, is
an increase in value. A bigger animal does make it of greater
value, which he might actually say, but that's not normally what people
do with a donkey. They use it as beasts of burden. By
the time it really dies of old age or something like that,
you know, it's—nobody's going to want to use it. I don't know
about dog food, but anyway. And therefore it's really just having a
fatter donkey, a bigger donkey is really no increase. Although again, I
don't know, because, you know, I mean, if the donkey keeps on
growing, obviously if it's bigger, it's—it's stronger, it's worth more. But I
guess the immediate— But I guess the immediate act of feeding it
food does not directly increase the value. And again, the question I
raise is the ר"ן Ran says that's only after it's had its
base meal already taken care of, but I would say no even
though you have saved it from starving that's a maintenance thing that's
not an increasing of value. Yes.
So I guess they're saying this over and over again that if
you pay my creditor, that's not a profit for me, that's maintenance?
Yeah, well that's a bizarre idea. Obviously. I know, but that's what
we keep on coming back to because that's seen as just preventing
a loss, that's not seen as directly giving me something of value.
All right, so we will end here today and we'll continue to
be a little behind.